<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Naumachia, or Hollands sea-fight</title>
            <author>Holland, Abraham, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839880</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4340</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4340)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1144:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Naumachia, or Hollands sea-fight</title>
                  <author>Holland, Abraham, d. 1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] P[urfoot] for Thomas Law, and William Garrat,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Abra: Holland.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ [par.]¹ 2[par.]²  B-D⁴.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lepanto, Battle of, 1571 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:1"/>
            <p>NAVMACHIA, <hi>OR HOLLANDS</hi> SEA-FIGHT.</p>
            <q>Non equidem inuideo.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Law,</hi> and <hi>William G<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rat. An. Dom.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable and Noble <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Gordon</hi> Sonne and Heire to the Right Generous and Potent, the <hi>Marqueſse</hi> of <hi>Huntley.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONOVRABLE, &amp;c. Although the obſcurenes both of my ſelfe and merits, may ſeeme to breed ſome preiudice of boldnes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in me, daring thus to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my ſelfe, and a ſmall worke of mine equall in merit to my ſelfe, to you a <hi>Heroe</hi> indued with no leſſe Goodneſſe, than greatnes, of equall Vertue and Honor, Of a like Courage &amp; Courteſie, of as much Clemencie as Valour, Paralels that ſiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome meet in one.</p>
            <p>Yet Fame the blazer of good Actions, reſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from yours, to our Coaſts, the report of your Honourable Courteſie and loue to good Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, I haue bin emboldned by this ſmall Preſent, to manifeſt the loue, or rather ſeruice I owe to your ſelfe and Honourable Name; a Name no leſſe knowne and renowned Abroad, than loued
<pb facs="tcp:4340:3"/> and honored at Home, as terrible to foes, as gtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and pleaſing vnto friends. And although the Noblenes of your honorable and ancient Progeny with the noble and Warlike actions of your Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous and renowned Father &amp; Anceſtors might yeild to you, their generous Of-spring, ſufficient cauſe of praiſe &amp; glory; yet you knowing, that the good parts of body, or proſperous caſualties of good Fortune, can ſcarce bee called or accounted our own; you I ſay to theſe haue added Vertue, the beauty &amp; ſtrength of mind, knowing that <hi>Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſola eſt atque unica virtus.</hi> This hath made you <hi>Non tibi ſed toti genetum te credere mundo</hi> Go on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generous <hi>Gordon,</hi> and by attaining the height of Vertue, obtaine the top of honour; Be you a Gem in the Vnion of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> follow the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of your renowned Father, and if it be poſſible in vertue out goe him; and according to your ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nererous diſpoſition accept this ſmall Preſent of your humble wel-wiſher, the gratious acceptance of which ſhal ſtir me vp to ſome greater endeavor wherby to eternize your Name and Vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sola<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non norint haec monumenta mori.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours to be commanded, <hi>Abra: Holland.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:3"/>
               <head>NOBILISSMO, ET GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſiſſimo Domino Georgio, comiti <hi>Ingeienſi Anagramma.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Georgius Gordonius comes Ingeienſis,</l>
                     <l>Egregio dignus enſi, ſic Muſis honor ego.</l>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <l>CLare, Caledonios, Heros aucture triumphos,</l>
               <l>Et Scotico titulos exhibiture Polo:</l>
               <l>Cuius et indomitos generoſi pectoris ignes,</l>
               <l>auxit, Hyperboreas, nix, populata plagas:</l>
               <l>Te<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, tuum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> genus claris inſigne Trophoeis,</l>
               <l>norunt Arctophylax, plauſtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pigra gelu,</l>
               <l>Plauſtra per vndoſos numquam ſubitura receſſus,</l>
               <l>dum videant vultus, ſidera grata, tuos.</l>
               <l>Tu long is lumen tenebris, et gente remota</l>
               <l>Pierijs gratam das Helicona choris.</l>
               <l>Te Phaebum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum putat et Caledonia Martem,</l>
               <l>qui fulges aequè Martis, et artis honor:</l>
               <l>Ergò armis te bella canant; te carmine Muſae,</l>
               <l>qui potes et Muſis et decus eſse tubae:</l>
               <l>Andraeas Scoticis, taceat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Georgius Anglis,</l>
               <l>hinc Scoticis Numen, Gorgius alter erit.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Honoris tui devotiſſimus.</hi> Ab: Holl.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:4"/>
               <head>To the ſame Noble Earle, two Acrosticke Stanza's.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glory in you is like the Sun, which giues</l>
                  <l>Eternall ſplendour, yet is often hid,</l>
                  <l>Ore-ſhadow'd in ſome clime, when yet he liues</l>
                  <l>Reviving ſtill: the world cannot forbid</l>
                  <l>Glory her beames; but like fires hid in night</l>
                  <l>Expreſſe at laſt a more refulgent light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Grace then the Muſes, who can giue you light,</l>
                  <l>Obliuion it ſelfe can neuer hide,</l>
                  <l>Reſpect thoſe Sacrifices, by whoſe might,</l>
                  <l>Demigods ſoone are wholly Deifide:</l>
                  <l>Onely giue pardon to me, who can giue</l>
                  <l>Nothing elſe yet, to make you longer liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:4"/>
               <head>¶ In Honor of the Noble Marqueſſe of <hi>Huntley, and his true Generous Sonne, the Lord</hi> GORDON.</head>
               <l>THE Royall Eagle <hi>Ioves</hi> owne Bird, to trie</l>
               <l>As they report her true borne Progenie,</l>
               <l>Ere ſhe admit them for her owne, or grace</l>
               <l>Them to be called of the Eagles race</l>
               <l>To <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes, and the ſight-dazing skie</l>
               <l>Sh' expoſes all her vnfleg'd infancy:</l>
               <l>And thoſe that beare the baſtard ſearching light</l>
               <l>With eyes vndazled, and with nobler ſight</l>
               <l>Can brooke the iudging flame, theſe as ſure-knowne</l>
               <l>Indulgently ſhe brings vp for her owne;</l>
               <l>But thoſe whoſe baſtard eyes cannot endure</l>
               <l>The piercing ſplendor of a light ſo pure,</l>
               <l>Theſe as falſe-got the Royall foule refuſes,</l>
               <l>And onely thoſe which ſhe hath tried, chooſes.</l>
               <l>Thus, Noble Lord your Father, whom of all</l>
               <l>We truely may the Northerne Eagle call,</l>
               <l>So doth he ſoare and ſtill aſpire aboue</l>
               <l>The vulgar pitch; ſo for the trueſt <hi>Ioue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath he in cruell wars borne venfull thunder,</l>
               <l>Bringing the barbarous High-land ſauage vnder:</l>
               <l>Wherein you his true Sonne he made to try</l>
               <l>The glorious ſunne of Magnanimity.</l>
               <l>Which you with noble mind ſo well endur'd,</l>
               <l>That hence your Father hath been well aſſur'd</l>
               <l>Of a true Sonne: So may both Sire and Son</l>
               <l>Be tri'de at vertues never-ſetting Sun.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:5"/>
               <head>To my friend M. <hi>A H.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>BY this one lim, my <hi>Holland,</hi> we may ſee</l>
               <l>What thou in time at thy full growth maiſt bee,</l>
               <l>Which wit, by her owne Symetrie can take,</l>
               <l>And thy proportion perfectly can make</l>
               <l>At thy Aſcendant: that when thou ſhalt ſhow</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe; who reads thee perfectly ſhall know</l>
               <l>Thoſe of the Muſes by this little light</l>
               <l>Saw before other where to take thy height.</l>
               <l>Proceed, let not <hi>Apollo's</hi> ſtocke decay,</l>
               <l>Poets and Kings are not borne euery day.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Michael Drayton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>To his louing friend M. <hi>Abra: Holland.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>SEnd forth, young man, from Muſes wombe,</l>
               <l>Thy other Royall births at home,</l>
               <l>But ſlowly, ſlowly ſend them forth</l>
               <l>Leaſt for their number, and their worth</l>
               <l>The enuious hand of fates take hold,</l>
               <l>And crop thee; for they'le thinke th'art old,</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ed: Cory.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:5"/>
               <head>To my Brother A. H.</head>
               <l>AS thy firſt Muſe doth wit and learning ſhow,</l>
               <l>So let true wiſdome with thy learning grow.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Brother,</hi> Hen. Holl.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>¶ Amico ſuo Abrahamo Hollando, D. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemonis F. in Naumachiam ſuam.</head>
               <l>NAumachiam luſtrando tuam, mihi flumine viſus,</l>
               <l>Ingenij placido deperijſe tui:</l>
               <l>Arma virum, tabulas, galeas, &amp; ſcuta per vndas</l>
               <l>Aſpicio, &amp; mens est Carmine merſa ſimul.</l>
               <l>Emergo! &amp; tabulas votivas dedico Muſae,</l>
               <l>Docte Hollande tua, quae bene ficta canit.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>El: Petl.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>To my honeſt friend M. <hi>A. H.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>That this ſmall peece the world ſhould hazard firſt,</l>
               <l>Of other better work's, thy Muſe hath nurſt;</l>
               <l>To wonder I was forc't, vnleſſe't be done</l>
               <l>As a ſmall ſtarre doth vſher forth the Sunne.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I. VV.</hi> I C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Caueat to his Muſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WEll Minion you'le be gadding forth then? goe,</l>
                  <l>Goe, haſt vnto thy ſpeedy ouerthrow:</l>
                  <l>And ſince thou wilt not take my warning: Hence,</l>
                  <l>Learne thy owne ruine by experience.</l>
                  <l>Alas poore Maid (if ſo I her may call</l>
                  <l>Who itches to be proſtitute to all</l>
                  <l>Adulterate cenſures) were it not for thee</l>
                  <l>Better, to liue in ſweet ſecuritie</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4340:6"/>
                  <l>In my ſmall cell, than flying raſhly out,</l>
                  <l>Be whoop't, and hiſſ't, and gaz'd at all about</l>
                  <l>Like a day-owle: Faith Miſtris you'le be put</l>
                  <l>One of theſe daies to ſerue ſome driveling ſlut,</l>
                  <l>To wrap her ſope in, or at leaſt be droven</l>
                  <l>To keepe a Pie from ſcorching in the Oven;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe expos'd a laughing ſtock to ſots,</l>
                  <l>To cloke Tobacco, or ſtop Muſtard pots,</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt be grac't if ſo thou canſt but win</l>
                  <l>To infold Frankincenſe or Mackrills in,</l>
                  <l>You deem't forſooth a matter of high worth</l>
                  <l>To haue a fame among'em: <hi>New come forth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thinke your chiefe felicity is marr'd</l>
                  <l>If you be not perch't vp in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard</l>
                  <l>Where men a farre may know you in a trice,</l>
                  <l>By ſome new-fangled, braſſe-cut Frontiſpice.</l>
                  <l>Such book's indeed as now-dayes can paſſe</l>
                  <l>Had need to haue their faces made of braſſe.</l>
                  <l>Is it not then ſufficient for you</l>
                  <l>To ſtay at home among the reſidue</l>
                  <l>Of better ſiſters: where my deareſt <hi>Will,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And other friends would praiſe and loue thee ſtill:</l>
                  <l>Him and my other harts-halfes I account</l>
                  <l>Intire aſſemblies, and thinke they ſurmount</l>
                  <l>A Globe of addle Gallants: I averre,</l>
                  <l>One iudging <hi>Plato</hi> worth a Theater.</l>
                  <l>But you me thinks of all the reſt ſhould feare</l>
                  <l>The ſearching rayes of cenſure, leaſt you bleare</l>
                  <l>You tender fame: who can chooſe but diſdaine</l>
                  <l>The firſt <hi>Minerua</hi> of an idle braine.</l>
                  <l>Pen'd ere I well was paſt a boy, or downe</l>
                  <l>With ſilken moſſe, my maiden chin did crowne.</l>
                  <l>Blacke <hi>Lycophron</hi> redeem'd of late by mee</l>
                  <l>From the darke graue of deepe obſcuritie,</l>
                  <l>And taught to ſtalke in Engliſh meaſures, dreads</l>
                  <l>The cenſure of the Beaſt with hundred Heads,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4340:6"/>
                  <l>And keeps cloſe home: like one from deepe of night</l>
                  <l>That cannot quickly brooke the dazling light.</l>
                  <l>My labour'd <hi>Merlin,</hi> Brittiſh <hi>Lycophron,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Still ſitteth in his dreary delue alone,</l>
                  <l>And as yet wary Prophecies, that who</l>
                  <l>Leape into'th world too ſoone, themſelues vndoe.</l>
                  <l>My devout Holy-dayes yet ſecret lurke,</l>
                  <l>And dare not frame themſelues vnto a worke.</l>
                  <l>My merry Paradoxes, ſtill laughing ſit,</l>
                  <l>And dare not mocke the world, in Publicke yet:</l>
                  <l>Yea my deare Syren-twins, keepe ſtill at home</l>
                  <l>Though almoſt fledg'd and ready now to rome</l>
                  <l>About the world: with hundred crotchets more,</l>
                  <l>My Patromonie, Portion, wealth and ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Yea and theſe riches ſo contentfull, I</l>
                  <l>Would not forgoe for all the Treaſury</l>
                  <l>Th' Exchequer holds) wilt thou then of them all</l>
                  <l>Dare in theſe times diſtracted clutches fall?</l>
                  <l>Oh, tis a way that ſpoiles things haply good</l>
                  <l>When itching youngſters crop themſelues i'th bud,</l>
                  <l>And ſo proue rotten before ripe, to win't,</l>
                  <l>That they may have their names but ſeene in print.</l>
                  <l>But ſeeke not thou about the world to gad</l>
                  <l>Before thou haſt an Eagles triall had;</l>
                  <l>Then dare to Impe thy full fledg'd wings and flie</l>
                  <l>Neerer than other Muſes to the skie.</l>
                  <l>Out-face the Sun, and ſing ſuch notes as may</l>
                  <l>Approue that thou art worthy of the day.</l>
                  <l>Great glory ſure they get and ſolide fame,</l>
                  <l>Who to obtaine a Month-enduring Name</l>
                  <l>Make monſtrous bookes, which did they fill the ſtalls,</l>
                  <l>Yea were they pil'd vp to the top of <hi>Paules</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would quickly vent, when for a month or two</l>
                  <l>One ſhall not paſſe but he ſhall heare adoe</l>
                  <l>And freſh enquiries for the booke; anon</l>
                  <l>Ye ſhall heare faintly, This, a yeare agon</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4340:7"/>
                  <l>Was a braue booke, this was a booke indeed.</l>
                  <l>Ah haples he who now is put to read</l>
                  <l>The jade-tir'd lines. Thus both ſuch bookes &amp; makers</l>
                  <l>Are both of ſame fame, and ſame fate partakers.</l>
                  <l>Liue for a day, and flouriſh, but at night,</l>
                  <l>Like the ſhort Roſes, vaniſh with the light.</l>
                  <l>But care not thou whether vaine fame doe giue</l>
                  <l>That thou doſt now, or maiſt heerafter liue.</l>
                  <l>And know that Poem's truely fram'd, relie</l>
                  <l>Not on the preſent but poſterity.</l>
                  <l>And learned Poets think't ſufficient gaine</l>
                  <l>If that they after death may but obtaine</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Poſtume</hi> glories: nor thinke that theſe times</l>
                  <l>Can rightly iudge of well deſeruing rimes,</l>
                  <l>We muſt expect another age, for this</l>
                  <l>Scarce knoweth whether proſe or Poem ti's.</l>
                  <l>For Poem's now admir'd, are onely thoſe</l>
                  <l>Change but the words a little they are proſe</l>
                  <l>As plaine as <hi>Holinſhed,</hi> each feeble line,</l>
                  <l>As foot-pac't as this poore <hi>L'envoy</hi> of mine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But tell me when thou into'th world art come</l>
                  <l>How wilt thou pleaſe the multitude, when ſome</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe thou canſt outbaudy <hi>Martial,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or looſe-pen'd <hi>Arbiter,</hi> will ſtiffly call</l>
                  <l>Thee ſlight and witleſſe: did but this clew lead thee,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Ladies then would daine to read thee</l>
                  <l>And in their perfum'd boſomes would infold</l>
                  <l>Thee willinger, than Chaines of Pearle and Gold,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Aristotles</hi> Problems: great men would make thee</l>
                  <l>Their nere companion, and to Church would take thee.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of Pſalmes (if ſo to Church they goe,</l>
                  <l>God knowes aboue whether they do or no.)</l>
                  <l>Others there are whoſe addle empty braines</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe thou fill with loue-ſicke-puling ſtraines</l>
                  <l>Will proue ſtarke made againſt thee: All in all</l>
                  <l>Would haue this garbe: the Prentice at his ſtall</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4340:7"/>
                  <l>Itching would buzze vpon thee: and each maid</l>
                  <l>That faine would yet dare not profeſſe the trade</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſh' ha's been well brought vp: Infinite</l>
                  <l>The number is will call thee Paraſite</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou medleſt not with any things</l>
                  <l>Touching the State, Embaſſadors or Kings,</l>
                  <l>O ſuch an one, ſay they: To theſe replie</l>
                  <l>So deare I will not my repentance buy,</l>
                  <l>Nor will I tread in ſuch vnequall meaſure,</l>
                  <l>As at my danger to procure you pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>But what I can, will ſtriue to blazon forth</l>
                  <l>My Countries honour and my Kings: the worth</l>
                  <l>Of any perſon who ſhall merit prayſe</l>
                  <l>For ſuch I watch and bite the frantick bayes</l>
                  <l>But the moſt part are ſuch as thoſe who vow</l>
                  <l>That Muſe is dull and drie whoſe crabed brow</l>
                  <l>Skoul's not forth Satires: the Meere title ſeene</l>
                  <l>But of a ſcourge excell's the Faery Queene.</l>
                  <l>To theſe ſay thus: would you haue me, a Muſe</l>
                  <l>So rude and vnexperienc't to abuſe</l>
                  <l>Her harmles quill? write ſatyres? That's the worke</l>
                  <l>of brazen pens, with danger that dare ierke</l>
                  <l>And ſweare their Inke from bluſhing: which expert</l>
                  <l>In the bad world dare venter to inſert</l>
                  <l>Particulars which makes the world to ſweare</l>
                  <l>They needs a part in wickedneſſe muſt beare</l>
                  <l>They open it ſo naked: ſuch their ſpirit</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> with them is <hi>Caſar</hi> if he merit:</l>
                  <l>For me to ſatyrize from blow-point age</l>
                  <l>Cloiſter'd in circuit of a college cage</l>
                  <l>where my experience of Ill nere flew</l>
                  <l>Beyond the lurching of a diſh or two,</l>
                  <l>Where ſophiſmes miſſ't were held crimes out of reaſon</l>
                  <l>And the not capping fellow's chiefeſt treaſon,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Libells there they hold of take</l>
                  <l>Some cowl-ſlaffe ſhew or witty Almanaka.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4340:8"/>
                  <l>And ſuch faults as are puniſht by the Deanes</l>
                  <l>I know not what a ſtates corruption meanes,</l>
                  <l>What bribery is; or what it is to wracke</l>
                  <l>The vulgar neckes, or breake the commons back</l>
                  <l>but ſatyriſts ſterne quill muſt rip vp faults</l>
                  <l>From womb of night whoſe acting makes the vaults</l>
                  <l>Of Heauen bluſh, which in a fearefull brood</l>
                  <l>Are hatch't by ſin and nourtred by blood</l>
                  <l>Headlong reuenge, Extortion, Orphans crie</l>
                  <l>Are fitt for them, and fearefull Leachery</l>
                  <l>But I a Muſe that drinke a milder Chalice</l>
                  <l>Shall I poore ſnake creepe in and ſting the malice</l>
                  <l>Of crimes more fit for <hi>Iuvenall,</hi> or him</l>
                  <l>That wrap't his laſhes in obſcure and dim</l>
                  <l>Clouds of reuenge, aſham'd to tell the crimes</l>
                  <l>Openly which were acted in thoſe times.</l>
                  <l>To liue in Court I nere ſo high could riſe</l>
                  <l>How ſhould I then begin to ſatyrize.</l>
                  <l>Nor am I yet ſo wicked as to bee</l>
                  <l>Experienc't in all iniquity</l>
                  <l>Which ſatyriſts muſt ſcourge: I ſhall in time</l>
                  <l>May be vnto the gall of ſatyres climbe</l>
                  <l>If this cannot content their quenit enquiry</l>
                  <l>Tell'em thou haſt a brazen pen, with fiery</l>
                  <l>Full fled'gd, heart-goring wings, a ſtubborne pen</l>
                  <l>Not to be ſpent on paper but on men</l>
                  <l>With inke ſteep't full of bitter gall. Now flie</l>
                  <l>Vpon the wings of humble modeſtie</l>
                  <l>And thy ſelfe happy herein vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>That thou muſt come to ſuch a <hi>Heroes</hi> hand</l>
                  <l>Whoſe onely name can free thee from the hate</l>
                  <l>Of vulgar preiudice, and vindicate</l>
                  <l>Thee from the Lethe of obliuion. Thus</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing to thee ſome lucky Genius</l>
                  <l>Farewell my Muſe: and think't a ſhame to ruſh</l>
                  <l>Into the world and ſeene there once, to bluſh.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:8"/>
            <head>NAVMACHIA, Or the Poeticall Deſcription of a <hi>Bloody</hi> Sea-fight.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Sun once lift vp his burning Lampe</l>
               <l>On top of hils, and fiery ſteeds gan ſtampe</l>
               <l>Along the blew-floor'd skie, the Charriotier</l>
               <l>Made his firce horſes run a full Carreir:</l>
               <l>He whipt 'em on, ſo that their blood there ſhed,</l>
               <l>Made the cleare Balcon of the Eaſt looke red.</l>
               <l>He poſted on as if he meant not ſtay</l>
               <l>To make a Summer, but a winters day:</l>
               <l>Or as if he had wager'd that his teame,</l>
               <l>Sooner than wont ſhould ſouze in weſtern ſtreame:</l>
               <l>The ſteeds themſelues with ſpeed vnvſuall flie,</l>
               <l>As frighted at this ſea-bred Prodigie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There came along cutting deepe <hi>Neptunes</hi> brow,</l>
               <l>A miſty maſſe, to call't I know not how:</l>
               <l>Whether a running Towne, or wauing Wood,</l>
               <l>Or moouing Delos tumbling on the Flood,</l>
               <l>Which ſeene a farre ſcud on the watry way,</l>
               <l>Prodigious <hi>Affrick</hi> ſeemd, or <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who getting <hi>Neptunes</hi> Paſ-port, came to ſee</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:9"/>
               <l>Their Siſter <hi>Europe</hi> in her brauery.</l>
               <l>At whoſe approch the curled billowes rore,</l>
               <l>And as it comes fearefully roll before.</l>
               <l>Th' oppreſſed tower-like Whales lie bellowing vnder,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Neptune</hi> ſeemes t' vſurpe his brothers thunder.</l>
               <l>The ſilent Fiſh preſaging future bloud,</l>
               <l>Againſt their kind run frighted into th' mud:</l>
               <l>And had they wings, would from the Sea haue broken,</l>
               <l>And but for churliſh nature would haue ſpoken</l>
               <l>To manifeſt their feare, yet what they might,</l>
               <l>They fled apace to ſhun the dreadfull ſight.</l>
               <l>And flying from the Sea in trembling ſhiuers,</l>
               <l>With their thicke ſholes peſter'd the leſſer riuers.</l>
               <l>The Oceans King feeling ſuch weight on's backe,</l>
               <l>With leaning on his Trident made it cracke.</l>
               <l>Had it not been immooveable, they ſay,</l>
               <l>The earth this time would faine haue fled away.</l>
               <l>Th' amazed ſhore as the fleet neere ſounds,</l>
               <l>Almoſt forgot to keep's ordained bounds.</l>
               <l>The earth and ſhore ſo trembling, you'd ha ſayd,</l>
               <l>Feare, not incloſed winds, this Earth-quake made.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fame with her feet on earth, and head i'th' ſpheares,</l>
               <l>With wings plum'd full of wonderment and feares,</l>
               <l>Flies ore the land, and forth her rumours blazes,</l>
               <l>And with increaſing dire reports amazes.</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt courages ſtill as ſhe goes,</l>
               <l>Sh' augments the power and valour of the foes.</l>
               <l>Tel's of ſtrange engines, inſtruments, and whips,</l>
               <l>Framed to act their cruelty, and ſhips</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:9"/>
               <l>Prodigious bigge, vizards, and murthering Kniues,</l>
               <l>Butcherly malls for ſlaughter, Halters, Giues,</l>
               <l>And all the men like Giants: Thus ſhe flies</l>
               <l>Increaſing ſtill the Terrour, and with lies</l>
               <l>Makes a true feare: and ere it was well ſpide,</l>
               <l>She ſweares the fleet in ſuch a place did ride.</l>
               <l>And all the men were landed: ſuch a towne,</l>
               <l>Was battered, and ſuch a caſtle downe.</l>
               <l>Another Citty without doubt was ta'ne,</l>
               <l>And at the winning of it, more men ſlaine</l>
               <l>Then it contain'd: Thus monſtrous Fame doth range her,</l>
               <l>And maketh feare more fearefull then the danger.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus as Fame her flying terrour doubles,</l>
               <l>Each diuers ſtate is wract with d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uers troubles.</l>
               <l>Great men doe feare that they here-by ſhall fall,</l>
               <l>Which the poore man doth hope to riſe withall.</l>
               <l>The peaceable do hereby feare annoyment,</l>
               <l>The needy Ding-thrift hereby hopes imployment.</l>
               <l>The Coward this way feareth he ſhall die:</l>
               <l>The valiant looke for immor<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ality.</l>
               <l>The louing Wife doth feare her Husbands life,</l>
               <l>And he as much is troubled for his Wife.</l>
               <l>Stout old men wiſh that they were young againe,</l>
               <l>Baſe young men wiſh that they in age were ta'ne:</l>
               <l>Women for feare weepe out their tender eyes,</l>
               <l>Dumpe Infants almoſt anſwer to their cryes.</l>
               <l>In all the diſagreement, which is here,</l>
               <l>They all agree in this, that all doe feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Beacons now were fir'd: as if the flame</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:10"/>
               <l>Euen here a contrarity did claime</l>
               <l>Againſt the water, whoſe prodigious light,</l>
               <l>Men feard on land, as in a ſtormy night</l>
               <l>The Sailers feare <hi>Orion,</hi> which but ſeene,</l>
               <l>Pronounces vnto Mariners, the teene</l>
               <l>Of angry clouds. And now thoſe noble Spirits,</l>
               <l>Whoſe onely ayme is by their haughty merits</l>
               <l>To out-liue fate, and for their Countries good</l>
               <l>Thinke it a glory to powre forth their blood,</l>
               <l>Meete all together, as deuote to giue</l>
               <l>Their owne liues that their Countrymen may liue.</l>
               <l>Thus in all ages, and we ſtill may trie</l>
               <l>Of life the worthi'ſt, readieſt are to die.</l>
               <l>Who haſting to their ſhips in ſpeed, begin</l>
               <l>To ſhew the aduerſe party ſhould not win</l>
               <l>Without reſiſtance, ſhewing there were made</l>
               <l>Men as well to defend as to invade.</l>
               <l>Our Admirall breath's forth a ſtout All-arme,</l>
               <l>The aduerſe fleet Ecchoed rebounding, Arme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As when by ſound of hollow braſſe, or tin</l>
               <l>The ſcatterd bees, buzzing with murmurous din,</l>
               <l>Throng in one heape, to ſome well-branched tree,</l>
               <l>Leauing their ſweet, and harmeleſſe the every;</l>
               <l>And ſo by craft betray'd, are in a trice</l>
               <l>Captiu'd all in their narrow Edifice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus at their Captaines voice, the vulgar ſort</l>
               <l>To their aſſigned ſtations reſort;</l>
               <l>With quicke confuſed haſt the tumult's led,</l>
               <l>And ſpeed, by too much ſpeed, is hindered.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:10"/>
               <l>All to their charge with trembling boldnes run,</l>
               <l>With quaking hand one charges firſt his Gun,</l>
               <l>Another girds his threatning ſword on's ſide;</l>
               <l>Some claſps their ſteelie Helmets; ſheilds are tied</l>
               <l>On trembling armes apace, that one might then</l>
               <l>Haue thought th' had been all mouing Iron men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now the Martiall ſteely-pointed ſtaues</l>
               <l>Were ſnatch't in haſt: the heauy murdring Glaues:</l>
               <l>Bowes bent to ſlaughter: weighty Courtelaxe:</l>
               <l>And Darts Death's Harbingers; the black bill, axe.</l>
               <l>And other armes which before ruſting ſtood,</l>
               <l>But now are brought forth to be skour'd with blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our ſaile-wing'd fleet launcheth fro' th'shore now eaſed</l>
               <l>Of it's dread burden, nor was th'earth more pleaſed</l>
               <l>To ſee from her one hideous terrour paſt,</l>
               <l>That grieu'd to ſee another come as faſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One might haue thought the battell was begun</l>
               <l>To ſee how <hi>Neptune</hi> firſt was thorough run,</l>
               <l>How the ſterne braſſe his curled forehead tore,</l>
               <l>And trembling waues were ſtrucke by cruell oare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each Fleet the Captaines had deuided ſoone,</l>
               <l>Into the formes of the halfe-circled Moone;</l>
               <l>But as their furious hornes together met,</l>
               <l>Theſe two halfe-moones a full Moone did beget;</l>
               <l>Which like to that in Heauen, as it did goe,</l>
               <l>Made the fleet waters ſtrangely Ebbe and Flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now as with proud aduance they neerer came,</l>
               <l>Thoſe beaſts which gaue the ſaile-rul'd veſſels name,</l>
               <l>With an aſpect more grim than is their life,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:11"/>
               <l>As breathing nought but bate, and balefull ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Come fiercely forward all, as if from thence</l>
               <l>They meant to moue their painted Reſidence.</l>
               <l>The Lyon, Elephant, and ſauage Hogge,</l>
               <l>The Libard, Tygre, Ounce, and cruell Dogge</l>
               <l>Sternely affront each other, one might gueſſe</l>
               <l>In midſt of Sea a ſauage Wilderneſſe,</l>
               <l>Wherein with admiration, one might ſee</l>
               <l>So many a fierce wild beaſt, ſo many a Tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now our valiant Generall traverſing</l>
               <l>About the fleet encourag'd them, rehearſing</l>
               <l>This ſpeech, wherein he brauely did exhort</l>
               <l>To th' Fight, which ready cut th' Oration ſhort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Courage braue friends, and that is all I pray,</l>
               <l>Strength cannot want, where Courage leads the way,</l>
               <l>But what need I th'vndaunted hearts excite,</l>
               <l>Of them whoſe eies me thinks already fight;</l>
               <l>Looke as ye doe, and ye ſhall neuer need</l>
               <l>Weapons, or hands to make your foes to bleed.</l>
               <l>Your look's ſhall ſtrike 'em dead, and warlike ſight</l>
               <l>Shall put your fearefull enemies to flight.</l>
               <l>What ere ye aime at, heere before you lie,</l>
               <l>Honour, Reuenge, Spoile, Riches, Victorie:</l>
               <l>Which if they mooue not, ſee your Natiue Land,</l>
               <l>Your Nurſe, your Mother, ſee how ſhe doth ſtand</l>
               <l>Afarre to marke, which of you beſt ſhall render</l>
               <l>The Meed of Nurture, who ſhall beſt defend her,</l>
               <l>Them will ſhe honour; brauely then driue backe</l>
               <l>This vaſt Sea-monſter, which is come to racke</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:11"/>
               <l>Your Nurſſes entrailes, com't but once to Land,</l>
               <l>The very Earth will be affraid to ſtand</l>
               <l>It's cruell brunt, whither if reach it can,</l>
               <l>The blood and teares will make an Ocean</l>
               <l>Deeper than this: I ſee'em now repaire</l>
               <l>(O let my <hi>Omen</hi> vaniſh into aire.)</l>
               <l>Vnto our Land; ſee how like Wolues they rage</l>
               <l>About the coaſts, ſparing nor ſex, nor age.</l>
               <l>See how they pull ſtrong wals of Citties downe,</l>
               <l>Leauing the men as naked as the Towne.</l>
               <l>They raze your ſacred Temples, and not leaue</l>
               <l>A hallowed place, where after ye may heaue</l>
               <l>Your hands for aide to heav'n: Your Altars frames,</l>
               <l>Theſe wicked wretches, with prophaned flames</l>
               <l>Sacrifice to their anger; yea they dare</l>
               <l>To open Ghoſtly Tomb's, and thence lay bare</l>
               <l>Your Anceſtors ſad Coffins: whoſe dead aſhes</l>
               <l>Inſtead of teares, their Childrens blood be-daſhes.</l>
               <l>They dragge our ancient Parents vnto ſlaughter,</l>
               <l>Anſwering their dying grones with cruell laughter.</l>
               <l>Our younger Wiues and Siſters they deflour,</l>
               <l>And baſel<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make our neereſt kinſmen, our</l>
               <l>Moſt hated foes; our tender infants rawle</l>
               <l>Scarce borne, being borne vnto their funerall.</l>
               <l>Theſe things, which, heav'n be thank't, I but ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe yee helpe will once aduance our foes.</l>
               <l>Say that our Nauy be farre leſſe than theirs,</l>
               <l>Haue not great ſhips, amids their ſwift carriers</l>
               <l>Beene ſtaid by little Remoraes: Then on,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:12"/>
               <l>And let not this cold Element, whereon</l>
               <l>We are to fight, quench thoſe couragious flames</l>
               <l>Which burne in euery manly breſt, that aimes</l>
               <l>At immortality, but ſtrike ſo ſterne,</l>
               <l>That the dumbe fiſhes may heereafter learne</l>
               <l>To ſpeake your praiſes, and each waue report</l>
               <l>Vnto it's neighbour, in how valiant ſort</l>
               <l>Ye fought, till that the Oceans vtmoſt bound,</l>
               <l>And fartheſt Thule with your fame ſhall ſound:</l>
               <l>Yea that the Sun, when he at night ſhall preſſe</l>
               <l>This way, may goe and tell th'Antipodes</l>
               <l>What acts he ſaw; nor yet of ayd deſpaire,</l>
               <l>The Sea it ſelfe, if need ſhall aske, will ſpare</l>
               <l>A thouſand of his ſtreaming arm's for you,</l>
               <l>All fiſh prooue ſword-fiſh to fight for our due.</l>
               <l>Thinke for no refuge heere to flie, your hand</l>
               <l>Not feet muſt bring you backe againe to land:</l>
               <l>No longer will the time with vs diſpence,</l>
               <l>What my ſpeech wants, my ſword ſhall recompence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now 'twixt a thouſand liues, a thouſand death's</l>
               <l>Of time one little winged minute breath's</l>
               <l>The loud-mouth'd Gun, onely expects the fire,</l>
               <l>At touch of which, as burnt, it ſhould expire</l>
               <l>It's skrieking voice, groning that ſo much death</l>
               <l>Should be accompliſh't by th'infectious breath</l>
               <l>Of it's dire mouth; Darts ready are to part</l>
               <l>To hide their heads in ſome ill fortun'd hart.</l>
               <l>Arrowes, and Muskets leuel'd, ſeeme to kill,</l>
               <l>Before they can in act, in fierie will.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:12"/>
               <l>One might haue thought viewing this fearefull ſight,</l>
               <l>'Thad bin the picture of a Navall Fight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But harke th' amazing ſignes of battell ſound,</l>
               <l>Making the lands remote, and rockes rebound:</l>
               <l>The ſhrill voic't Trumpet and couragious drum,</l>
               <l>In barbarous language bid the foes to come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Death's horrid vizar now begins t' appeare,</l>
               <l>In their pale faces; terrour, and gaſtly feare</l>
               <l>In their amazed hearts doth panting riſe,</l>
               <l>And future blood bath's in their fiery eyes.</l>
               <l>Sterne Cruelty aduanceth in their lids,</l>
               <l>With headlong fury ſtalking in the mids:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apelles</hi> preſent here or one ſo skil'd,</l>
               <l>Might haue made pictures hence that would haue kil'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The thundring Ord'nance now began to rent</l>
               <l>Th' amazed aire, the flames before it ſent,</l>
               <l>Seeme lightning, and as deadly bullets flie:</l>
               <l>Prodigious haile ſeem'd to powre downe the skie,</l>
               <l>Smoake made a clowdy miſt, and all together</l>
               <l>Seeme on the ſea to make tempeſtuous weather.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To call for ayd here, ſtands as much inſtead,</l>
               <l>As in that place, when from a doubtfull head.</l>
               <l>The ſeauen-mouth'd <hi>Nilus,</hi> with a deſperate ſhocke,</l>
               <l>Headlong doth tumble from th' amazed rock;</l>
               <l>Making the people on the neighbouring ſhelues,</l>
               <l>That hearing him, they cannot heare themſelues;</l>
               <l>Thus the fights noyſe made many a man to fall</l>
               <l>In troublous death, a ſilent Funerall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas thoſe Elements which vſe t' vp hold</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Our crazy liues, with their iuſt heate, and cold,</l>
               <l>Making compact our bodies conſtitution,</l>
               <l>Striue now to cauſe it's vtter diſſolution</l>
               <l>The quicke and piercing fire, as it doth burne</l>
               <l>Their wofull carkaſſes, doth freezing turne</l>
               <l>Their minds to quaking feare, and chill deſpaire,</l>
               <l>The liquid, flitting, and all-ſearching aire</l>
               <l>Admitts remorſles ſhot, and murdring darts</l>
               <l>Denying breath at laſt to coole their harts.</l>
               <l>The theeviſh water though it ran away</l>
               <l>With ſuttle ſhifts, did notwithſtanding ſlay</l>
               <l>And ſwallow moſt, with a deuouring flood,</l>
               <l>Onely poore earth, ſtarke, ſtill, aſtoniſhed ſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who viewing this would not haue thought a wonder</l>
               <l>That without raine, wind, lightning, haile, or thunder</l>
               <l>Or hidden ſhelues, or rocks ſea-ambuſht back</l>
               <l>Or any temreſt, ſhips ſhould ſuffer wrack?</l>
               <l>That one might heere haue term'd it, chooſe you whether</l>
               <l>A ſtrong Calme, or calme tempeſtuous wether.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See winged arrowes poſting through the skie</l>
               <l>How quicke they haſt froth' battells rage to flie</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The trembling ſpeares, as ſouldiers doe them ſhake,</l>
               <l>Seeme at their Maiſters dangrs that they quake:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The flaſhing ſwords, which ſheathed once they ware,</l>
               <l>Seeme now to feare, being vnarm'd and bare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now each fleet, each ſhip with hope-full pride</l>
               <l>Claſh altogether, furious, ſide to ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As when two winds in blacke tempeſtuous wether,</l>
               <l>With boiſtrous wings impetuous meete together</l>
               <l>With their vntamed and reſiſtles iuſtle,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:13"/>
               <l>Making high turrets ſhake, and cedars ruſtle,</l>
               <l>Where in light ſhirmiſh they remaine contending,</l>
               <l>Till out of breath th' are faine to make an ending</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now death's at hand, and night together keepe</l>
               <l>Cleare life, and dreadfull death's blacke iron ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Fierce rage, ſad griefe, blind Fury now grow higher,</l>
               <l>Good cauſe when ſence of touch and hearing nigher</l>
               <l>Men now with men contend, and ſhips with ſhips,</l>
               <l>One body 'gainſt another; here one skips</l>
               <l>Into his enemies deck, but beaten back</l>
               <l>He leaps to's owne, of which if ſo he lacke,</l>
               <l>He fall's in ſea; much like a wave, whoſe head</l>
               <l>By vrging winds vnto the ſhore is led,</l>
               <l>And thence by breſt of the oft-drowned ſhore</l>
               <l>Taking a blunt repulſe, for ſpight doth rore,</l>
               <l>And ſtaggering runs backe; and is this all</l>
               <l>Ambition aymes at, in the way to fall?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Their tired ſences labour'd in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>That they grew dull with too much excerciſe</l>
               <l>Their troubled eyes, viewing ſuch gaſtly ſights,</l>
               <l>Wiſht that ſad darkeneſſe cancell'd all their hights:</l>
               <l>That horrid noiſe the battell made, was ſuch,</l>
               <l>Hearing heard nothing, 'cavſe it heard ſo much</l>
               <l>Taſt is of death, ranke blod pollutes the ſmell,</l>
               <l>What feeling felt they all did feele too well.</l>
               <l>Such a confuſion racks their ſenſes here</l>
               <l>Th' had Reaſon now to wiſh they ſenceleſſe were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grim death in purple, ſtalkes vpon the hatches,</l>
               <l>With pale and grieſly lookes ſee how he ſnatches</l>
               <l>Hundreds a once vnto him, till the dreary</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:14"/>
               <l>Lean-face't ill-favord Death of death grew weary.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See on the ſea how thouſand Bodies float</l>
               <l>From their great ſhips haſting to <hi>Charons</hi> Boat,</l>
               <l>Which crabbed Skuller now might thinke it meet</l>
               <l>His old-torne Boate ſhould be new-chang'd a Fleet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The tumults noiſe pierc't the blew-arched skie</l>
               <l>The chryſtall Aire fill'd with a deadly crie,</l>
               <l>Onely in this was bleſt, as blowes abounded,</l>
               <l>It could be euer cut, yet neuer wounded.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſilent Earth glad that ſhee was debarr'd</l>
               <l>From this ſad Fight, yet inwardly was heard</l>
               <l>The dreadfull ſtrokes rebounding loud, to mone</l>
               <l>And Eccho made her yeeld a hollow grone,</l>
               <l>But this cauſe chiefly made her moſt to raue,</l>
               <l>That to her due the ſea ſhould prooue a graue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neuer did ſtrong-breath't <hi>Aeolus</hi> diſturbe</l>
               <l>The ſea ſo much, When he can hardly curbe</l>
               <l>His madding pages, when they raging muſter</l>
               <l>To quarrell with the waues, or whiſtling bluſter</l>
               <l>Among the well-ſet trees, and branched bowgh's</l>
               <l>Singing through chinks of ſome decayd houſe:</l>
               <l>Nor ſterne <hi>Orion</hi> with his ſtormy light</l>
               <l>Appalling ſhipmen, doth ſo much affright</l>
               <l>The ſoone moov'd ſea, as did this battels noiſe,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Neptune</hi> anſwer'd with his bellowing voice,</l>
               <l>Who as the Fleet's vrg'd neerer to the ſtrand</l>
               <l>Which tumbling pace, ran frighted vp the ſand,</l>
               <l>That had not bounds reſtrain'd his element,</l>
               <l>His watery vaile had cloth'd the Continent.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:14"/>
               <l>The fearefull winds on th' Ocean durſt not rome,</l>
               <l>But leaſt they ſhould be ſmother'd kert at home.</l>
               <l>And there ſat ſighing: Clouds their rane doe keepe,</l>
               <l>Though ready at the battells ſight to weepe,</l>
               <l>Leaſt their pure drops with gore-blood ſhould be ſtaind</l>
               <l>So that no winds blew, nor from heauen it rain'd;</l>
               <l>Maruaile not yet at tempeſts on the flood</l>
               <l>So many teares ſtream'd, and ſuch ſtreames of blood,</l>
               <l>Nor without winds are waues to be admir'd,</l>
               <l>So many grones and dyings brea'ths expir'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Oceans</hi> skaly, ſilent wandring nation</l>
               <l>Seeing pale armed troups inuade the ſtation</l>
               <l>Of their vaſt kingdome, downe the ſanguine flood</l>
               <l>Fearefully glide, fearing their future food.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The tender Nymph's who with their ſiluer feete</l>
               <l>Vſe on the plaines of criſped Thetys meete,</l>
               <l>Where tripping prettely th' are wont to dance</l>
               <l>Themſelues, into a heauenly ſlwmbring trance</l>
               <l>Of ſweet repoſe, at theſe in humane ſhocks</l>
               <l>With haire all torne creepe into th' hollow rockes</l>
               <l>Wher ſhrouded they to meditate began,</l>
               <l>No rocke ſo flinty as the heart of man,</l>
               <l>The rocks though alwaies ſtruck by waters fury,</l>
               <l>The rockes yet patient beare this iniury;</l>
               <l>Yea <hi>Thetis</hi> ſelfe whoſe woombe enriched bare</l>
               <l>That fearefull Thunder of the Troian war</l>
               <l>Stubborne Achilles, who in fight did win</l>
               <l>Such glory, wiſht that warr's had neuer bin.</l>
               <l>So ſhe, with all her trembling watery peers</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:15"/>
               <l>Augment the briniſh ſea, with briniſh teares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ships now begin to burne, that one might ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neptunes</hi> and <hi>Vulcans</hi> conſangunity</l>
               <l>Yea now theſe ſhips, which free from water ſtood,</l>
               <l>Strangly begin to ſinke with humane blood,</l>
               <l>Which as from thence with fearefull guſh it ran,</l>
               <l>Fill'd vp the wrinkles of the Ocean,</l>
               <l>Making with purpoſe gaſtly gored hue,</l>
               <l>Of one Red ſea which was before, now two:</l>
               <l>Which ſea ſo full of Dead, it hence might come</l>
               <l>Well to be called, <hi>Mare Mortuum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The quaking ſhips with murmuring guns are rent,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wounded ſides the gored ſtreames doe vent</l>
               <l>Of dead and wounded men, who lay therein,</l>
               <l>As if they had their Beeres or coffin's bin:</l>
               <l>They lay therein and as the ſhips did goe</l>
               <l>Seem'd bloody, bloodles, dead, and mooving too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The furious fire with flames doth vndermine</l>
               <l>The towring Maſt, made of the lofty Pine,</l>
               <l>So that ſame tree which oft hight's Nuptiall's,</l>
               <l>Now Cypreſſe-like doth burne at Funerall's.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And eaten by the galling flames, at laſt</l>
               <l>Fall's downe the huge, high, heauy weighted Maſt,</l>
               <l>And as great things are wont, fell not alone</l>
               <l>Killing a troupe nor of it's foes, but owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The tacklings, ſail's, and cables now doe burne,</l>
               <l>And fire caſts Anchors, neuer to returne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>About their eares the whiſtling bullets ſung,</l>
               <l>And wandring wild-fire made th' affrighted throng</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:15"/>
               <l>Croud into corners ſpeedily, and they</l>
               <l>That durſt ſtand men, to ſenſles fire giue way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As when with in the fat Trinacrianſoile,</l>
               <l>Inflamed <hi>Aetna</hi> doth begin to boile,</l>
               <l>When nak't <hi>Pyracmon,</hi> with his round-ey'd fellowes,</l>
               <l>Sweatinh heaue vp their huge ſtrong-breathed bellowes,</l>
               <l>Thundring vpon their ſteeled Anviles top</l>
               <l>To furniſh armour for their ſmoaky ſhop;</l>
               <l>Their pondrous hammers, and redoubling, makes</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enceladus</hi> belch out his ſulph'ry flakes</l>
               <l>Of veng-full wrath, then may you ſee blackeſmoke</l>
               <l>Vomiring out, wrapt, in a pitchy cloke,</l>
               <l>And the hard bowels of the mountaine, torne</l>
               <l>By fetter'd fire, with a ſtrange bounding borne</l>
               <l>Vp to the cloulds, whoſe fearefull fall to ſhun,</l>
               <l>The neighbouring people with a maz'ment, run</l>
               <l>To ſhroudin'g Dens, hiding them cloſely vnder,</l>
               <l>Fearing from high, and from below a thunder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then did th' inhumane battels fury rage,</l>
               <l>Nor could the ſea th' increaſing flames aſſwage.</l>
               <l>And Mars himſelfe, in Adamantine armes,</l>
               <l>With a hoarſe voice rores out againſt all-armes,</l>
               <l>He that would now haue travailed to hell,</l>
               <l>Might haue ſeene weary ſweating <hi>Charon</hi> well</l>
               <l>In feruent labour, with his moſſy oares</l>
               <l>Tugging pale ſhaddowes to th' ore-ſwarmed ſhores;</l>
               <l>Which on the bancks as they lamenting crept,</l>
               <l>Wailing <hi>Cocytus</hi> in compaſſion wept.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acheron</hi> flow'd with griefe, and as they ſay,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:16"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lethe</hi> it ſelfe could neuer forget this day,</l>
               <l>The Furies whin'd, by <hi>Plutoes</hi> Iudgement caſt,</l>
               <l>Who ſware their rage was farre by men ſurpaſt,</l>
               <l>One coming heere might tired <hi>Clotho</hi> ſpie,</l>
               <l>How ſhe could fearſe her weary arm's apply</l>
               <l>To turne the wheele; and <hi>Lacheſis</hi> repine</l>
               <l>Who ſware ſhe could not threds of mortalls twine</l>
               <l>So faſt as they were cut; you might haue ſeene</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atropos</hi> raging with remorſles teene</l>
               <l>And ſeeking each where for ſome greetty ſtone</l>
               <l>To whet her ſheeres, whoſe edge was dulled growne</l>
               <l>With too much cutting of their fatall thread,</l>
               <l>Whoſe haples liues this gaſtfull battell ſhed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fire now and water did not each contend,</l>
               <l>But ſeeme their power ſo mutually to lend,</l>
               <l>That at this time there many a one became</l>
               <l>Burn't in the ſea and drowned in the flame.</l>
               <l>This one good hap to carkaſſes did fall,</l>
               <l>Th' had fire to burn 'em at their funerall.</l>
               <l>The mangled ſhips not fearing to be drencht,</l>
               <l>Gladly take breaches, thereby to be quencht.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now thou <hi>Tiſiphonc,</hi> infernall Muſe</l>
               <l>Rouzing thy ſelfe from Stygian ſleepe, peruſe</l>
               <l>The various Images of dreary Fate</l>
               <l>Hapning in this ſad Fight, and Intimate</l>
               <l>Them to my mind, which well, I thinke, agree,</l>
               <l>Not with a ſweete, and heauenly Muſe, but thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Th' Induſtrious Pilot ſitting at the ſterne,</l>
               <l>VVhere in a little card, he can diſcerne</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:16"/>
               <l>The vaſt vncertainetie of <hi>Neptunes</hi> haunt</l>
               <l>Ruling ſwift ſhips by powerfull Adamant,</l>
               <l>Here as he ſits retir'd, and watchfull minds</l>
               <l>The frequent change of two and thirty winds</l>
               <l>Comes an vnruly ſhot, and him doth force</l>
               <l>To certaine death, change his vncertaine courſe,</l>
               <l>So he that wont ſtern blaſts in truce to bind,</l>
               <l>Could not foreſee when he ſhould looſe his wind,</l>
               <l>From ſtormes, and Miſts of Death he could not free</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, who wont the Tempeſts curbe, but he</l>
               <l>Who bearding <hi>Neptune,</hi> vs'd on th' Ocean float,</l>
               <l>Is now controll'd in <hi>Charons</hi> little boat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Maſter ranging vp and downe the Deck,</l>
               <l>And wounded mortally, to him doth beck</l>
               <l>His Mate, who haſting to his ayd in vaine</l>
               <l>Is there together with the Maiſter ſlaine,</l>
               <l>And at once ended with him his liues Date,</l>
               <l>Proouing himſelfe truely the Maſters Mate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Trumpetter, with braue reuiuing ſound</l>
               <l>Quickning their dying harts, is fell'd toth' ground,</l>
               <l>And as in's mouth he ſtill the braſſe did wield,</l>
               <l>His dying breath made it a dead march yeeld,</l>
               <l>And hauing lent his Trumpet ſo much breath</l>
               <l>In's life, it turn'd him ſome againe at's death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Drummer with his nimble hand repeating</l>
               <l>His doubled blowes, without compaſſion beating</l>
               <l>His harmleſſe drum, which ſeem'd with groning cry</l>
               <l>To murmur at his Maiſters cruelty,</l>
               <l>Sodenly two raſh bullets rudely come</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:17"/>
               <l>Tearing both skin of drumer, and the Drum,</l>
               <l>Drummer of life, of ſound the Drum's bereft:</l>
               <l>So Drum, and Drummer both are ſpeechles left.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Gunner as with nimble haſt he runs</l>
               <l>To fire his ſeldome-vaine-reporting Guns,</l>
               <l>His head a leaden-winged bullet hits</l>
               <l>And his hard braine-pan into peeces ſplits,</l>
               <l>He of a thouſand this alone might vaunt,</l>
               <l>That of his death he was not ignorant,</l>
               <l>And this true riddle might of him abide,</l>
               <l>He liued once by's Death, by's life now dide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here comes a Captaine, with vndaunted face,</l>
               <l>Encouraging his ſouldiers to the Chace,</l>
               <l>And being about to ſay, be braue and bold,</l>
               <l>An vntaught bullet rudely bids him hold,</l>
               <l>And as death's miſt in his dull eyes did wander,</l>
               <l>Beſeeching ayd he left to be commander,</l>
               <l>And he whoſe voice from fainting thought to call them,</l>
               <l>By's dying grone doth fearefully apall them:</l>
               <l>This leader faithfull to his vtmoſt breath</l>
               <l>Can onely now lead them the way to Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See how to ſteale the wauing flagg, one climbs</l>
               <l>Vp by the cards, but being eſpied betimes</l>
               <l>Tangled i'th' ropes, he is of life bereft,</l>
               <l>And ſo is hang'd for his intended Theft.</l>
               <l>But the cords burnt wherin his leggs were bound,</l>
               <l>He gets a Pirats death both hang'd and drown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some vnder hatches cloſed, in deſpaire</l>
               <l>Mount vp their foes with powder into the aire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:17"/>
               <l>Which done it ſeem'd a ſtrange prodigious ſight</l>
               <l>A troupe of armed men to maske the light:</l>
               <l>It ſeemeth yet that they no damage meant 'em,</l>
               <l>Who the next way vp into heauen ſent 'em</l>
               <l>Making them flie, beyond <hi>Dae dalian</hi> skill,</l>
               <l>In the vaſt aire, without a winged quill,</l>
               <l>Giuing to them a ſtrange vnwonted death,</l>
               <l>Who hauing aire too much yet wanted breath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See ſee the lot of ſad Mortality,</l>
               <l>Our chiefeſt help's, helpe oft to Miſerie,</l>
               <l>Some men who came ſecure from future harmes</l>
               <l>Inroll'd in well-proou'd ſteely clothed armes.</l>
               <l>Fall by miſchance into the ſea's dire hand,</l>
               <l>Whence being vnarm'd they might haue ſworn to land:</l>
               <l>Their armes doe ſinke, and without mercy end 'em</l>
               <l>So kill'd by that which chiefly ſhould defend 'em.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One with his Musket ready to giue fire</l>
               <l>Aymes at another aduerſe Muskettier,</l>
               <l>But his match miſſing fire, hee's forc't to die</l>
               <l>By the others matches true fidelity,</l>
               <l>By which he di'de, can ſcarc'ly well be knowne,</l>
               <l>Whether by th' others Musket or his owne.</l>
               <l>See there a Coward wanting heart t' abide</l>
               <l>The daunting face of the fierce aduerſe ſide,</l>
               <l>Slinketh behind the next, not caring whither,</l>
               <l>Comes a mad ſhot, and kill's 'em both together;</l>
               <l>Praiſe him in this, for though his life outdar'd him</l>
               <l>To equall th' other, yet his death compar'd him.</l>
               <l>Neuertheles if truly ye doe mind him,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:18"/>
               <l>As in his life, in's death he came behind him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One ſeeming now his ſide begin to faile</l>
               <l>Shew's them their colours, while himſelfe lookes pale,</l>
               <l>Sure by this man ſome Omen ill was ſhowne,</l>
               <l>To keepe their colours, who could looſe his owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thoſe men who chanced in the ſhips to fall</l>
               <l>The cruell ſea was made their buirall.</l>
               <l>And into th' waues without remorſe were throwne,</l>
               <l>Poore men, ſlaine by their foes, drownd by their owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Fiſherman who nigh them cut the Maine</l>
               <l>Sitting in's boate was with a bullet ſlaine,</l>
               <l>And the barke fir'd wherein he dead did fall.</l>
               <l>Which gratis, burnt, gaue him his Funerall</l>
               <l>True to thy Maiſter, kind boat, who with him</l>
               <l>Didſt oft in life, and now in death do'ſt ſwim</l>
               <l>With him aliue in water that didſt tire</l>
               <l>Thy waue-beat ſides, dy'ſt now with him in fire.</l>
               <l>Yet me thinks thou ſhouldeſt not deſerue this turne</l>
               <l>Who ſo oft plung'd with him which ſhouldeſt burne,</l>
               <l>Yet ſaile with him t' <hi>Elyſium,</hi> ſaile the faſter,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Carons</hi> ſtead that thou maiſt waft thy Maiſter,</l>
               <l>Strang Boat which thus we not amiſſe may call</l>
               <l>His Life, Death, <hi>Charon</hi> and his Funerall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Noble man that was a Renegate,</l>
               <l>While he againſt his King doth boldly prate,</l>
               <l>A ſhot takes off his head, as if twere reaſon</l>
               <l>That he ſhould be beheaded for his Treaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A baſer fellow while he dares complaine</l>
               <l>And raile againſt his once owne Soveraigne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:18"/>
               <l>A true Liege-man, as he thus boldly brags,</l>
               <l>Striketh him vp, and his vile body drags</l>
               <l>About the ſhip, and while he vainely begs,</l>
               <l>Remoſles cutteth off his armes and legs,</l>
               <l>And thinking then to throw him in the tide</l>
               <l>Hee's caught vpon an Anchor on the ſide,</l>
               <l>That one beholding rightly might haue ſed,</l>
               <l>He iuſtly was hang'd, drawne, and quartered.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some fearing ſwords, into the ſea doe flie,</l>
               <l>And ſo for feare of death, feare not to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some fall into the Ocean ſtain'd with gore,</l>
               <l>Which from their former wounds had guſht before,</l>
               <l>Which kill'd not them, as it from them was ſpil'd,</l>
               <l>But entring into them againe, th' are kil'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heeres one about to ſtrike, his foe doth fall</l>
               <l>Into the ſea, before he can recall</l>
               <l>His erring ſtroke, ſtriking the ſea to ſtay him,</l>
               <l>The Ocean in revenge o'th blow doth ſlay him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One fearing death doth faine to die and bleed,</l>
               <l>And while he is in faining, dies indeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Another being about to ſtrike his foe</l>
               <l>Looſeth at once his arme and threatning blow:</l>
               <l>His left arme ſhiuering, reaches at the other,</l>
               <l>But cut atwaine, lies with it's equall Brother,</l>
               <l>Both ioyn'd, though both devided, as in ſpight</l>
               <l>Of Death, they meant to part their laſt good-night,</l>
               <l>By ſhaking hands: the miſerable truncke</l>
               <l>As loth to part, fainting vpon them ſunke.</l>
               <l>One ſeeing them together thus, might ſay,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:19"/>
               <l>There a whole bodie, all in peeces lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See two with ſturdy grapple, ſtriuing whether</l>
               <l>Should overcome, both fall in ſea together;</l>
               <l>Embracing both till they haue loſt their breath,</l>
               <l>And ſeeme though foes in life, yet friends in death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two brothers ſlaine, as they together ſtood,</l>
               <l>One then might ſweare, they were allied in blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Other two, who ſo nigh reſembling, were</l>
               <l>A lov'd miſtake vnto the parents deare,</l>
               <l>(Cruell death ſever'd them) and that one left</l>
               <l>Poore parents knew, of errour now bereft:</l>
               <l>He left eternall cauſe of griefe renewes,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill aliue, ſtill his dead brother ſhew's:</l>
               <l>And yet to them this comfort ſtill he giues,</l>
               <l>Th' one cannot die, ſo long as th'other liues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The wounded ſouldiers, now that all elſe failes,</l>
               <l>To ſtop their wounds, doe teare their woful ſailes:</l>
               <l>Poore men who after they were overthrowne</l>
               <l>Had torne thoſe wings, wherby they might haue flown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One with his bleeding ready to expire,</l>
               <l>Thinks with his blood, to quench the ſhip on fire:</l>
               <l>And ſo in mids of flames he bleeding ſtands,</l>
               <l>Tearing new wounds with his kind cruell hands.</l>
               <l>And grieu'd to ſee his blood ſo little profit,</l>
               <l>He oft adds teares to helpe the quenching of it.</l>
               <l>Till at laſt fainting he is faine to fall,</l>
               <l>Into the ſea, which made his Funerall:</l>
               <l>And bleeding in it from each mangled lim,</l>
               <l>He quenched it, and it extinguiſh't him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:19"/>
               <l>See a poore wretch with both armes cut aſunder,</l>
               <l>Diſtracted leapt into the water vnder</l>
               <l>Meaning to ſwim, but ſee the wofull wretch</l>
               <l>With how much toile he laboureth to ſtretch</l>
               <l>His raw-veind ſtumps, which for his armes before</l>
               <l>Guſh nothing now, but ſtreames of deadly gore:</l>
               <l>Faine would he catch t'vphold his wavering life</l>
               <l>Some kind remaine o'th ſhip, but all his ſtrife</l>
               <l>Doth make him ſooner to be out of breath,</l>
               <l>And wanting armes he yet embraces death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One getteth this, by hauing loſt his eies,</l>
               <l>In that he cannot ſee his miſeries,</l>
               <l>Anothers legges are gone, that who him ſees</l>
               <l>Might thinke he did begge pardon on his knees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What refuge now is left? when if they ſhun</l>
               <l>Th'approaching ſword, into the fire they run:</l>
               <l>Shunning the fire, they into waterfall,</l>
               <l>So no way wants a certaine Funerall.</l>
               <l>Thus after ſtrange vnheard of ſort they lie,</l>
               <l>And death, by many deaths, makes one man die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The mangled ſhips no longer can withſtand</l>
               <l>Th'intruding ſea, and <hi>Mars</hi> his fiery brand;</l>
               <l>But ſinking downward one might then haue thought</l>
               <l>Them gone t' helpe <hi>Charon</hi> to waft ore his fraught.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The conquer'd fleet prickt now with deſperate ſtings</l>
               <l>Of horror, wiſh their army did of wings</l>
               <l>Onely conſiſt; but now as if it ſtood</l>
               <l>Tyed with faſt anchors to the ſtubborne flood</l>
               <l>Mooues not away, but void of all inſtruction,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4340:20"/>
               <l>Venter their owne, to haſten the deſtruction</l>
               <l>Of their once Maiſters, who into corners creepe,</l>
               <l>As among Wolues, a flocke of trembling ſheepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Much like a ſilly Doue, whoſe broken wing</l>
               <l>Hath tried the Talons of the aiery King,</l>
               <l>And lieth panting on the bloody ground</l>
               <l>Striving to flie from's enemies rebound.</l>
               <l>Alas poore bird, it wants that winged oare</l>
               <l>Which ſhould it's wonted ſcape to it reſtore:</l>
               <l>And ſo at length with ſilent patience crouching,</l>
               <l>It's made a prey to the fierce bird encroching.</l>
               <l>Thus fleet and bird lie i'th ſame wofull plight,</l>
               <l>Whoſe onely wiſh is to be put to flight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Sunne no longer could endure to ſee</l>
               <l>'Mongſt humane men ſuch inhumanity:</l>
               <l>Therefore his Horſes, bathing in their fome,</l>
               <l>With poſting ſpeed haſt to their watrie home.</l>
               <l>Where yet a while they all amazed flood,</l>
               <l>Finding in ſtead of Sea, a Sea of Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4340:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
